Mike Ruhl

2020 Fenton St Edgewater CO 80214 269-779-3811 | mikeruhl@me.com | linkedin.com/in/mikeruhl

SUMMARY

Lead software engineer with 14 years of experience in producing business-critical applications in the financial and healthcare industry. Technical project lead on multiple projects spanning regulatory, feature-driven, greenfield, and risk-reduction objectives. Strong, polyglot developer with a record of delivering quality software on time. Four years of experience with Azure as a lead architect on a cloud-based application, working on infrastructure, monitoring, deployment, and scaling. Total of 6 years working in Azure designing distributed systems.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

<u>Languages/Platforms</u>: .NET: C#, .NET Framework, .NET Core, .NET 5/6/7/8, ASP.NET MVC, WCF, Web API 2, WPF, Windows Forms, XAML, LINQ, Autofac, Microsoft T-SQL, Oracle PL/SQL, KQL, Razor, T4, Terraform, Azure ARM, Kubernetes, Docker. **Go:** Mux, Gin, **Frontend:** Javascript, Typescript, HTML, React, React Native, Expo, Electron, Gatsby

Operating Systems: Windows Server, Windows, Linux Ubuntu, OSX

Hosted: MSMQ, IIS, Azure, Azure Devops, Nuget, git, JIRA, Confluence

Web Technologies: REST, SOAP, JWT, OpenID, OAuth2, SCIM

<u>Cloud Technologies:</u> Azure: Web Apps, Functions, Service Fabric, VM/VMSS, Networking, Storage, Azure SQL, ServiceBus, Azure AD/Entra, Docker, Kubernetes, Managed

Kubernetes (AKS), Linkerd, Redis, RabbitMQ, Traefik, Okta, Kafka, Red Panda

<u>Databases</u>: Sql Server, Oracle 12c, MySQL, MariaDB, Sqlite, CosmosDB, MongoDB,

ElasticSearch

<u>Methodologies/Patterns</u>: Agile, Waterfall, MVVM, MVC, SOLID, TDD, CI/CD, microservices, Domain Driven Design, Event Storming, User Story Mapping

<u>DevOps/Agile Tooling</u>: Github, Azure DevOps, TFS, Gitlab, Teamcity, Octopus Deploy, Google Play Store, App Store Connect, Apple Developer, Microsoft App Center, JIRA, Confluence, Bitbucket

EXPERIENCE

Optimizely, Remote- Staff Software Engineer, Identity Platform

APRIL 2022 - PRESENT

Built an identity platform to enable single sign-on among disparate applications all in different stages of maturity from acquisition. This system is built in C# and uses Azure

Functions to run across geographic regions while using Okta to manage token generation and validation.

- Worked with product teams to onboard their application into our identity solution.
- Strengthened our deployment cycle by introducing the team to the testing pyramid, along with writing an integration testing framework for Azure's Isolated Functions.
- Built functionality around multi-tenant and software-as-a-service product solutions in order to provide best practices for OIDC token-level scoping.
- Led effort to implement SCIM protocol within our SSO solution such that our B2B customers could easily control provisioning within our products via their own directory services.
- Develop and maintain React frontend for logging in and maintaining users.
- Work directly with customers to onboard them to SSO and SCIM, along with troubleshooting integration with their identity systems.

Migrated web hook messaging system to kafka:

- Greatly improved eventing system by migrating from a centralized webhook system to kafka.
- Reduced message size and complexity by transforming changed states into JSON
 Patch payloads for consumers to quickly make delta changes. This enabled
 consumers to better understand the context of the change along with updating
 the new state in their system.
- Dramatically reduced failure rate by not requiring subscribers to be online to receive messages by reversing dependency back to the eventing system.

Integrate Acquired Products into the Optimizely One ecosystem:

- Facilitate onboarding of new products.
- Migration of existing customers into the Optimizely One platform.
- Consult with product teams on cross-product collaboration using our SSO solution.

Tobii Dynavox, Pittsburgh- Lead Software Engineer, Systems Integration

AUGUST 2021 - APRIL 2022

Returned to serve as lead engineer for backend services.

 Completed resource migration across tenants and multiple subscriptions of thousands of resources with minimal downtime and no production incidents.

Gateway Health Plan, Pittsburgh- Team Manager, Application Development

APRIL 2021 - AUGUST 2021

Serving as the team manager of the company's internal development team. Guiding team to implement modern development practices in an effort to streamline deployments, reduce technical debt, and produce more robust applications used by internal employees and the provider network.

Tobii Dynavox, Pittsburgh- Lead Software Engineer, Systems Integration

APRIL 2018 - APRIL 2021

Serving as the lead software engineer on our microservice platform, integrating several products' services within it.

- Led complete rewrite of client platform from web-based Flash application to desktop/mobile shared codebase using Xamarin and Electron.
- Technical lead and architect on all Education channel projects, specifically with Azure and .NET (Framework and Core) technologies.
- Develop reporting, dashboards, and alerts in Azure using KQL, Azure Monitor, and Application Insights to maintain service health and be alerted on outages.
- Migrated from Teamcity and Octopus Deploy to Azure Devops and implemented a full CI/CD pipeline.
- Partnered with QA to shorten release interval from several months to < 2 weeks by implementing unit, automated UI, and integration testing to boost confidence in releases.
- Implemented the microservice pattern using Service Fabric to deliver a scalable backend api that could coexist with the existing WCF services currently running in an Azure Web App, which enabled services to scale independently and upgrade without downtime.
- Mentored and paired program with team's developers to share knowledge on design patterns and best practices.
- Led Lunch and Learn series to keep the entire RND team up to date on current technologies we use within Azure and within the larger developer community.
- Implemented a shared Terraform system where resources in Azure could be provisioned and configured as part of the deployment process.
- Developed a recommendation system using Python and Keras.
- Led the infrastructure design and migration from centrally-located to globally distributed web application.
- Led the infrastructure design, implementation, and migration from SQL Server to AzureSQL, a database as a service.
- Leading project to migrate from Service Fabric to Kubernetes.

PNC Bank, Pittsburgh-Lead Application Developer in Retail Banking

OCT 2017 - APRIL 2018

Serving as the lead application developer on 3 applications for internal software utilized by several thousand employees in call centers.

- Technical lead on projects spanning small features to full datacenter migrations.
- Manage 4 developers: assigning tasks, reviewing pull requests, and pair programming.

- Develop for a web application, desktop application, and back-end systems on Windows.
- Modernizing a 13 year old code base by adhering to modern design principles such as MVVM and SOLID. Used Inversion of Control and Dependency Injection (Prism, Unity) to make the application more testable, reliable, and maintainable.
- Wrote a database migration tool migrating a 1TB database from Sql Server to Oracle.
- Technical lead on reporting application migration costing \$1.2mil and managed 24 contracted developers.
- Release coordinator, designing and developing continuous development pipeline in Team Foundation Server deploying to IIS, database, and application servers via IBM UrbanCode along with deploying to an Artifactory NuGet repository.

PNC Bank, Pittsburgh - *Sr Application Developer for Call Center Desktop Software*JUNE 2012 - OCT 2017

- Developed on desktop software used by call center employees to manage customer information while on calls. This software uses CTI to transfer data between automated systems and agents using Genesys and internally developed systems.
- Worked on many projects spanning multiple tiers: database design, desktop application development in WPF, and back-end services communicating through MSMQ.
- Tracked and resolved production bugs with the team as they came in using JIRA and VersionOne.
- Utilized git and SVN source repositories to commit code and build for releases.
- Worked on Waterfall and Agile projects in the developer role, contributing to releases and participating in scrums and sprint sessions.

PNC Bank, Pittsburgh - *Sr Operations Engineer for Call Center Technology* JANUARY 2010 - JUNE 2012

- Operations support for internal desktop software using shared services across bank (Windows Server) and the automated telephone system (Red Hat Linux).
- Rotated On-Call for support in both Windows and Linux clusters and systems, maintaining business critical applications for bank with high availability 24/7.
- Wrote internal information and monitoring tools to improve application reliability.

EDUCATION

Western Michigan University, Kalamazoo MI - *MA* - *Human Resource Development* 2005 - 2011

Western Michigan University, Kalamazoo MI - BA - Social Psychology